[SPEAKER_00]: So, a couple of suttas, maybe, on a similar theme.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the sangita nikāya, the saḷāyatana, the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: 153.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus, there is a method...
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, no, he asks the monks.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus, is there a method by means of which bhikkhu, from a place other than faith, other than preference, other than tradition,
[SPEAKER_00]: Other than an examination of properties, other than relying upon the insight from a view,
[SPEAKER_01]: Just examination of the properties.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's basically psychologizing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how I... basically, it's hard to translate these terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but I sort of was thinking about... Yeah, it's exactly like... just examining... just informing yourself about the properties, observing the properties of the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You mistake for understanding the nature of the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is the nature of, basically, the core of psychology.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's akāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: Parivrttika.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, thinking about the akhāra, which could be the... what makes the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, what it's made of.
[SPEAKER_00]: What it's made of.
[SPEAKER_00]: Properties.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Its qualities, or...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Its components.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Analysis, for the sake of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... Where are we?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, from a place other than those, is there a method by means of which a bhikkhu might describe final knowledge?
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, I understand that birth is destroyed, the whole life has been lived, what should be done has been done, there's no more of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the bhikkhus say, I don't know, you tell us.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha says, yes, there is.
[SPEAKER_00]: He then says, and which bhikkhus is the method by means of which a bhikkhu from a place other than faith, so on, might describe final knowledge, thus, I understand, but has destroyed, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he says, here, bhikkhus, a bhikkhu, having seen a sight with the eye, when there is passion, aversion, distraction internally,
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands.
[SPEAKER_00]: For me, there is passion, aversion, distraction internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: That passion, aversion, distraction is just a compound word.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not these different things.
[SPEAKER_00]: He just says passion, aversion, distraction, ragga, dosa, moha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basis of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In another place, like the roots of the unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's Madhyamini 9, where he says the roots to unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, so having seen...
[SPEAKER_00]: When there is passion, aversion, distraction internally, he understands, for me, there is passion, aversion, distraction internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: When there isn't passion, aversion, distraction internally, he understands, for me, there isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands there isn't this internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's clear about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by the way, when we speak, when you say the necessary basis for things, that's what a root is.
[SPEAKER_01]: A root is a necessary basis for the existence of a tree.
[SPEAKER_01]: The root doesn't disappear once the trunk starts to grow.
[SPEAKER_01]: It needs to be there throughout.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can have the trunk disappear, not the root necessarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if the root disappears, the trunk cannot remain living.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the root of the unwholesome...
[SPEAKER_00]: The root of the unwholesome is a necessary basis for unwholesome, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whenever you read about the root in the sutta, that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_01]: Necessary basis for this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding the necessary basis for greed and lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: Necessary basis for aversion, for destruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you'll see probably later, I guess, but based on where that sutta is going, not understanding what necessary basis is, is what provides the necessary basis for these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding the mind with greed, aversion, delusion, is already a step closer to overcoming the greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's simple, simply, once...
[SPEAKER_00]: As paschal version destruction, if those... the necessary basis for wholesomeness is there, either you know it's there, or you don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: And see, so that's the method.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Method is not to look in front of you, not to psychologize, not to be examining the properties, or just adhering to it blindly because the tradition told you so, or the authority of the teacher told you so.
[SPEAKER_01]: The method is to discern the background,
[SPEAKER_01]: Peripherally, what state of mind you are in, while this is happening to me in the front.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by seeing sight with the eye, instead of, hmm, what did I see?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it made of?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where it came from?
[SPEAKER_01]: How it came to be?
[SPEAKER_01]: How does it affect me?
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that is in the front.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that is rooted in you not seeing the state of mind simultaneously present with that sight, on account of that sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sure, yeah, there is a method which is completely opposite direction of any notion of method people might have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, usually, method is methodical analysis... Yeah, I mean, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...performance.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, no, as a word, method is absolutely fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just what people do on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know how to...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know how you talk about a way... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, there's nothing wrong with it, with a word in itself, with a term.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is... this is a form of a method as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: But a method that you cannot observe, psychologize, measure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or decide beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is it... it's something... it's somewhere other than faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not to say that faith is necessarily a bad thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: But faith is there in the front.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You place faith in things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to start practicing or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it is necessary in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's... That's what we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a different direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Faith cannot arrive at this.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not fake, not preference.
[SPEAKER_01]: No preference.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want this, I don't want that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tradition or from what you've heard, doing it because... Just watch your nostrils, just pay attention to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this examination of properties, breaking it down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Analysis, apologizing, scientific pontification.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, everything is constantly changing and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all just made up of these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just explaining everything nicely and neatly in front.
[SPEAKER_00]: Relying on insight from a view, that's again a speculative translation, but I say that...
[SPEAKER_00]: I take that to mean something like... Well, that's as literal as I can get, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: The insight from a view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nidjana, the insight from a view, and then...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the result of a certain view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I think of it as being like having some kind of understanding based upon a view, which is sort of applying to what's in front.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're extending
[SPEAKER_01]: The principle that you get from your view, as in you're not seeing it directly, you just sort of... if this is the case here, so it's to this extent, because that's how you understood the case in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, yeah, you can be holding on to a view, and because of that not seeing your current state of the mind, because you're reinterpreting it from the point of view that you have on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which kind of makes it, again, influence...
[SPEAKER_00]: Applying an external template on...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: External template that has been created on account of some insight of some view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right or wrong doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: By the way, even the right view works the same way.
[SPEAKER_01]: You create the right template, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when arahant is beyond the view, beyond the template.
[SPEAKER_01]: He has fulfilled the template.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's the Buddha's words on loving-kindness, anapagammas, dittīṃ anapagamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not having, not going into a view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not wrong views or fixed views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not still depending on the view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he says... he asks the monks, he says... Bhikkhus, for a bhikkhu having... who has seen a sight with the eye, for whom there's passion, aversion, distraction internally, and who understands, for me, there is passion, aversion, distraction internally,
[SPEAKER_00]: All for a bhikkhu, having seen, who's seen a sight with the eye, for whom there isn't passion, aversion, distraction internally, who understands, for me, there isn't passion, aversion, distraction internally, bhikkhus, are these things to be known by means of faith?
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are they to be known by means of preference?
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are they to be known by means of tradition?
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: By an examination of properties?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's amongst all of the, the entire domain where these, these things apply.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can only be known directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, or are they... yeah, well, no, lying on the inside from the views.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the monks say, no, can't take it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus, he says, are these things to be known having seen them with understanding?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, can't take it.
[SPEAKER_00]: This, bhikkhus, is the method by means of which a bhikkhu, from a place other than faith, tradition, etc., might describe final knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the method is to know the background of your method.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of your faith, of your observances, of your analysis, of your traditional techniques.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you know the background of it, you're going beyond the method.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, yeah, you can call that a right method.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it can only be seen
[SPEAKER_01]: Through understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, seeing it means understanding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And understanding in the sense of... And understanding means dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, completely.
[SPEAKER_00]: But understanding, not just... not just... No, understanding what exactly what it says.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not understanding the contents of this particular thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's you examining the properties and then kind of classifying and collecting them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding what state of mind is simultaneously present with this simultaneously enduring sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What state of mind is simultaneously present with this simultaneously enduring feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it the state of mind with passion?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it the state of mind free from passion?
[SPEAKER_01]: Know that to its extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means you're getting to know the nature of the phenomenon that your mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if there is passion, aversion, distraction there... You know it as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you see, so not kind of shrinking away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, now I need to do something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to know it to the extent that it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the problem is not in those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is not even in that mind, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is you not understanding its extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you either go too close, too far, trying to overly affirm it, overly deny.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get involved, you get burdened by the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it becomes your passion, your everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you certainly, it's not a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another preference.
[SPEAKER_01]: To just choose to... okay, I will not have these states of mind, because they're unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha asked, can you obtain these things by preference?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you can't choose your way out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you know the state of mind within the present enduring choice, towards sight, towards feeling, towards whatever, that's how you step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not something you can look at directly, which would be a matter of choice, a matter of examination.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's sort of discerning the... the proper route.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the proper necessary basis, which is always peripheral from where you look.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because normally... That's a definition of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...the route would be me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the assuming.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the default.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is, see, the sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, it's always in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always the perception of it has to be in front.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is not in front.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you could see, that's what all these things have in common.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're also in front.
[SPEAKER_01]: Examination, preference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I just have clarity of information what needs to be done, told, passed down to me by tradition, by requirement, and I'll do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all in the front.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all where the senses are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, the real method is actually completely the opposite direction, defined by what's not in front.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't see your mind on the level of the sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the lust is not in the sight, it's in the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, all you keep doing, in order to get rid of the lust in the mind, is examining the sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you are unsuccessful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Manipulating, preventing, controlling, denying, indulging, all these, like, revolts against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Completely misplaced.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't know that there is simultaneously a present enduring root of that significance of that whole sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: And everything that's pressuring you, bothering you, or exciting you, whatever, whichever sight it is, the necessary root is the state of mind effectively lost, or the state of mind non-effectively lost.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to train that peripheral vision.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot, like, find a way that will then enable you to look at it directly and, okay, now I'm done.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, pick up the sign.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pick up the sign of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: The necessary condition for the arising of right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Become familiar with the sign of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sign of the phenomenon of the mind, for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, for as long as you assume that you can observe your mind on the level of the senses, with a method of observation, means you don't know what the nature of the mind is, which means you're ignorant of its signs.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why always, like, when we're doing those previous interrogations, like, what is your current mood?
[SPEAKER_01]: How you feel?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's already a background of whatever you're doing now, trying to understand now, want to say now, want to deal with it now.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're in a certain mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where you start looking for your mind, in the direction where your mood is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not something you can put in front of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you performing effort of putting something in front is on the basis of that, within that container of that mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: The entire life of the tree is contained within the existence of the roots.
[SPEAKER_01]: Functioning roots, present roots.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter how big the tree gets, its life is always within the basis of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if that disappears, none of the extent of the tree can remain.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a different sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this root of the unwholesome, Anguttara, Book of Threes, the Buddha says there are these three grounds for the arising of action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which three?
[SPEAKER_00]: Lobha, so I'm going to translate as desire is the ground for the arising of action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Aversion is a ground for the arising of action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance is a ground for the arising of action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever action is done with desire, born of desire, grounded in desire, arisen out of desire,
[SPEAKER_00]: Wherever self-existence is born, there that action bears fruit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wherever that action bears fruit, there one experiences the result of that action, either in this life, or having been reborn in some other way, or arising in some other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever action is done with aversion, whatever action is done with ignorance,
[SPEAKER_00]: Or delusion, or distraction, or born of ignorance, grounded in ignorance, arisen out of ignorance, wherever self-existence is born, there that action ripens.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever that... wherever that action ripens, there one experiences the result of that action, either in this very life, or having arisen in some other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suppose, bhikkhus, some seeds that were not broken, not rotten, not spoiled by wind and heat, taken from the most excellent part, well embedded, laid in the good ground, were laid in the good ground, in well-prepared earth, and the sky would provide the right amount of rain.
[SPEAKER_00]: These seeds, bhikkhus, will undergo an increased growth abundance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And just this way, bhikkhus, whatever action is done with desire,
[SPEAKER_00]: I've done with aversion, I've done with ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wherever self-existence is born, there that action ripens.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wherever that action ripens, there one experiences the result of that action, either in this very life, or having loosed in some other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just these... the idea of these... the root, the necessary basis... of... of action, in this case, action.
[SPEAKER_01]: What about... Maybe this isn't going to kind of... Well, it kind of sounds pretty much straightforward.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever you choose to act, you will do so in regard to how you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can... otherwise, you can say that there's... there is... for... for an unenlightened mind, there is only one basis of action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_01]: Action by body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That basis is craving towards feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which of these routes of greed?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which can be craving through greed, craving through aversion, craving through distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: What it is, is basically your response to a feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yeah, you can respond to the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your attitude towards the feeling that you've been subjected to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasant, unpleasant, or neither unpleasant or pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the... and that there cannot be any other action on the level of kamma that will have its ripening, as the Buddha describes it, unless it's rooted in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, if you learn how to act,
[SPEAKER_01]: Without being rooted in craving, you will be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why that does not constitute the action on the level of karma and vipāka, because there is no craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not done by him, for him, for others.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that whole domain is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Domain that's been existing on account of greed, aversion, delusion being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's the second part of the synthesis.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's these three grounds.
[SPEAKER_00]: The arising of action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which three?
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-influence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever an action... whatever action is done with non-desire, born of non-desire, grown up in non-desire, arisen out of non-desire, being without desire, in this way, that action is abandoned, put off at the root, made like a construct.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever action is done without craving, it's not an action anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The action is abundant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's internal state of mind determines whether you act or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not what you do externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can be then observed by others.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, there are certain things that you cannot do once the craving is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Have sexual intercourse, intentionally kill somebody, lie and things like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Many other things can be done by both.
[SPEAKER_01]: By an arahant and by a pūtujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can both eat, they both walk, talk, choose, prefer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But one is action, the other one isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because one is rooted in craving how he feels at the time, the other one is not rooted in that, because he doesn't feel anything anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the roots of the action for the arahant is non-desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The necessary basis for...
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not really action, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, if you decide to call it an action, sure, but then you need to understand it's not the action of Patujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the same action of Patujana, because as the Buddha describes, one results in this whole mess of suffering right now, or even later, or both.
[SPEAKER_01]: The other one is cut off its root right there and then, because he hasn't been done by clarity.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no vipaka, there's no result from this, so it's not really an action.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not an action, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you were to learn how can you act without needing to crave and desire the action, you'll be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you'll be at least a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you then develop that type of action, you will be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what we spoke before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, see, you think you act only when you're kind of aware of what you want to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even now, while we're talking, my hands are moving, my feet change position.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the body keeps acting in its own domain, in its own regard.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you regard that as secondary to my action that I choose to voluntarily, volitionally perform.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason you can choose and perform things with extra layer of volition is because the body allows you to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means the domain of this random movements of the body, breathing, shifting, changing postures, standing up, going to the toilet, eating, all of that, that is on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: And those are already actions that don't require craving to be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're all right... all you're doing when you're...
[SPEAKER_00]: Intentionally, I'm going to put my hand in the air now.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're basically bringing awareness to this whole domain of stuff that's there anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you're not the creator of any of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're within it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your volition is secondary to the domain where you can exercise it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's usually my volition is the center of the action and these are all its results and repercussions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, rooting all of those actions that are going on already.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's that's that's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, see, people don't... if people can't differentiate this, that's when you start to blame everything and nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I need to move, I can't move my leg, I can't do this, I can't do that, because that's craving, that's craving, that's craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't have this, I can't have that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that in itself, that response is an action.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already something you fully do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's more like... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all the way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all these things are done, they don't need the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let me just make a point then, when I'm aware that I'm acting out of craving, not do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if you accidentally kill somebody, it's not a murder.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's an accident.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what I'm referring to is, like, volitionally performing these actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why...
[SPEAKER_01]: It requires this kind of... a certain perpetuation of the level of craving, desire for action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the extent of it cannot be done by an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't have that at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it talks about greed, aversion, destruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a non-greed, non-aversion, non-distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's simply restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the starting point.
[SPEAKER_01]: And see, there's another interesting thing here.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that Kaya said, by not understanding this, you put your volition first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think that's the root.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then...
[SPEAKER_01]: You try to sort of even practice the dhamma through that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by that, I mean, you become aware that the body has its own domain where it does all these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to keep thinking about all these little movements, postures, scratching.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now you realize, but I must be aware of everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but instead of seeing that your volition is secondary, and by understanding the right order, you become aware of it, you try to then sort of subjugate everything to your volition.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's when you get the vipassana techniques of, oh, I can't just be aware of my obvious desires and cravings.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must be volitionally aware of
[SPEAKER_01]: Sitting, sitting, moving, talking, touching, touching, leaving...
[SPEAKER_01]: Ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not just...
[SPEAKER_00]: I shouldn't just be aware of the fact that I'm walking, but rising...
[SPEAKER_01]: I must keep bringing my volition.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bring volition, bring volition.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I missed a bit then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Failing to see that what you're doing is actually trying to force practice of dhamma through the wrong order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're trying to put yourself first.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it doesn't matter how much volitionally you commit to it, you're committing to your wrong view of what comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But instead, you need to recognize that all this lifting, putting, sitting, persisting, scratching, is done by the body on that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So just don't lose the corner of your eye.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to attend to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: By becoming familiar with the actions that don't need your attending, your volition, you're becoming familiar with the actions that don't require craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you can relax.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, all I need to do is stay at the gate in case the craving comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's not, I have no...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't need to stop and search everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's not the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, I know where the craving is there, when the aversion is there, when the desire for distraction is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I don't act out of.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is always, as I said before in previous talks, that is always intentional.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot unintentionally choose a desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: It always implies awareness of that choice, which means you're always responsible for choosing desire, aversion and distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead of trying to override everything with your completely misconceived volition, you have to start including the volition as secondary to all these little things that you actually do throughout the day, and you just need to remain aware of them peripherally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just know that it's being done, not specifically to what extent and how fast I'm moving my leg.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the body postures are the general reference points.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter what I do now, as long as I keep a corner of the eye that this body, this lump of flesh is seated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever is done, has to be done within that posture.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I have a choice to get up, to change the posture.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a volitional choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even that can eventually become normal.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a need to stand up.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll stand up.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't need to always attend to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead of trying to override everything with your volition, start including, basically, your volition as second to everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason you can choose, you can will things, is because there is a body, in its own domain, performing all these things anyway, anyhow.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you add an extra layer of, I want this, I want that, and that extra layer is completely gratuitously rooted in desire, aversion and distraction, which you then take to become first, which you put first.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is no beginning, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, this cannot be first.
[SPEAKER_01]: It shouldn't be first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not knowing that, you put it first, and there is no first point when that mistake manifests there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is your starting point.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is your resistance, which is why it's irreversible, once you undo it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you become an arahant, you cannot
[SPEAKER_01]: Reverse the picture and go back to the order of kutujana, because it's impossible for that order to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, knowing that, that's how you place it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Turns out, we have a lot to say about it.